<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
	<info>
		<name>Minotaur race from Tome of Heroes</name>
		<author url="https://koboldpress.com/kpstore/product/tome-of-heroes-for-5th-edition/">Kobold Press</author>
		<update version="0.0.1">
			<file name="race-minotaur.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Saerbhreathach/TOH-aurora/main/tome-of-heroes/race-minotaur.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>

	<element name="Minotaur" type="Race" source="Tome of Heroes" id="ID_KBP_TOH_RACE_ERINA">
		<description>
			<p>Minotaurs are imposing and powerful, with a reputation for ferocity that borders on monstrous. They display their achievements proudly by decorating their horns with engraved sigils and designs. If one is versed in minotaur custom, one can tell at a glance the achievements and prowess of a minotaur by examining the decoration on her horns. A minotaur who loses part or all of a horn suffers considerable stigma and must strive to prove their worth. Sometimes a “brokehorn” (a fighting insult to any minotaur) who manages to achieve great deeds earns the gift of having the missing horn magically restored by a temple. Beware any minotaur that willingly gives up or chooses not to restore a lost horn, for this is one of the world’s most driven and dangerous creatures.</p>
			<h4>TERROR ON THE HIGH SEAS</h4>
			<p>Minotaurs are a force to be reckoned with in a stand-up fight. Perhaps somewhat against type for their bulk, they are an absolute terror on the sea. Their corsairs have carved a tale of bloody blades and shattered hulls on the water, and even the world’s mightiest navies have learned to respect them. The minotaur’s natural sense of direction makes them ideal navigators on sea as well as land. Cover of night, fog thick enough to carve, and unfamiliar coastlines don’t phase the bull-folk.</p>
			<h4>TWISTING PATHS</h4>
			<p>Minotaur architecture and city planning always incorporate a particular design: labyrinths. Every settlement and structure of any size created by the bull-folk sports a twisting labyrinth of switchbacks and dead ends. In their largest cities, the city’s leader or reigning monarch lives in a palace at the center of a great labyrinth. At night, the clash of arms and screams of the dying find their way out of the maze. It is said that minotaur leaders invite both friends and enemies to enjoy the hospitality of these palaces, but only their friends survive the stay.</p>
			<h4>MINOTAUR NAMES</h4>
			<p>Most minotaurs have two names: a first name, which is often the same as their father’s or mother’s name, plus a descriptor. No matter how many children a minotaur has, odds are most of the males will have the same first name as their father and most of the females will have the same first name as their mother. The descriptors vary, but they’re aspirational rather than earned. Since the descriptors are given by the parents when the minotaur is still an infant, they might or might not turn out to be accurate. For example, parents who want their child to be a great warrior might call it “the Fierce.” If that minotaur grows up to become a poet rather than a warrior, it will still be called “the Fierce.”</p>
			<p><span class="feature">Male Names:</span>Aewigr, Kamdoth, Korwyn, Krolm, Ordwar, Rankoth, Thargad, Theodar, Theonco, Vorkhul</p>
			<p><span class="feature">Female Names:</span>Afridde, Brytredda, Chothuk, Gunda, Hrunan, Sedruse, Thariff, Thewenn, Varala, Wentheon</p>
			<p><span class="feature">Descriptors:</span>the Brave, the Intimidating, the Mighty, the Never-Lost, the Reaver, the Swift, the Unstoppable, the Unyielding</p>
			<h4>MINOTAUR TRAITS</h4>
			<p>Your minotaur character has certain characteristics in common with all other minotaurs.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability Score Increase.</em></strong> Your Strength score increases by 2, and your Constitution score increases by 1.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Age.</em></strong> Minotaurs age at roughly the same rate as humans but mature 3 years earlier. Childhood ends around the age of 10 and adulthood is celebrated at 15.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Alignment.</em></strong> Minotaurs possess a wide range of alignments, just as humans do. Mixing a love for personal freedom and respect for history and tradition, the majority of minotaurs fall into neutral alignments.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Size.</em></strong> Adult males can reach a height of 7 feet, with females averaging 3 inches shorter. Your size is Medium.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Speed.</em></strong> Your base walking speed is 30 feet.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Darkvision.</em></strong> You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can’t discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Natural Attacks.</em></strong> Your horns are sturdy and sharp. Your horns are a natural melee weapon, which you can use to make unarmed strikes. When you hit with your horns, they deal piercing damage equal to 1d6 + your Strength modifier, instead of the bludgeoning damage normal for an unarmed strike.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Charge.</em></strong> Once per turn, if you move at least 10 feet toward a target and hit it with a horn attack in the same turn, you deal an extra 1d6 piercing damage and you can shove the target up to 5 feet as a bonus action. At 11th level, when you shove a creature with Charge, you can push it up to 10 feet instead. You can use this trait a number of times per day equal to your Constitution modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Labyrinth Sense.</em></strong> You can retrace without error any path you have previously taken, with no ability check.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Languages.</em></strong> You can speak, read, and write Common and Minotaur.</p>
			<h4>ALTERNATIVE MINOTAUR TRAITS</h4>
			<p>At your GM’s discretion, you can create a minotaur character from the wetlands or highlands. Such minotaurs are known as bhain kwai (for those from wetlands) or boghaid (for those from highlands), and they each exhibit a few traits different from typical minotaurs. </p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<setters>
			<set name="names" type="male">Aewigr, Kamdoth, Korwyn, Krolm, Ordwar, Rankoth, Thargad, Theodar, Theonco, Vorkhul</set>
			<set name="names" type="female">Afridde, Brytredda, Chothuk, Gunda, Hrunan, Sedruse, Thariff, Thewenn, Varala, Wentheon</set>
			<set name="names" type="descriptor">the Brave, the Fierce, the Intimidating, the Mighty, the Never-Lost, the Reaver, the Swift, the Unstoppable, the Unyielding</set>
			<set name="names-format">{{name}} {{descriptor}}</set>
		</setters>
		<rules>
			<stat name="strength" value="2" requirements="!(ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI|ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_ABILITY_SCORE)" />
			<stat name="constitution" value="1" requirements="!(ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI|ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_ABILITY_SCORE)" />
            <select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +2 (Minotaur)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 2" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +1 (Minotaur)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 1" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<stat name="innate speed" value="30" bonus="base" />
			<grant type="Size" id="ID_SIZE_MEDIUM" />
			<grant type="Vision" id="ID_VISION_DARKVISION" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_KBP_TOH_MINOTAUR_RACIAL_TRAIT_NATURAL_ATTACKS" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_KBP_TOH_MINOTAUR_RACIAL_TRAIT_CHARGE" requirements="!ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_RACE_MINOTAUR_CHARGE" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_KBP_TOH_MINOTAUR_RACIAL_TRAIT_LABYRINTH_SENSE" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_COMMON" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_LANGUAGE" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_MINOTAUR" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_LANGUAGE" />
			<select type="Language" name="Customized Language" supports="Custom Race Language" number="2"  requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_LANGUAGE" />
			<select type="Race Variant" name="Minotaur Variant" supports="Minotaur" optional="true" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	
	<element name="Natural Attacks" type="Racial Trait" source="Tome of Heroes" id="ID_KBP_TOH_MINOTAUR_RACIAL_TRAIT_NATURAL_ATTACKS">
		<description>
			<p>Your horns are sturdy and sharp. Your horns are a natural melee weapon, which you can use to make unarmed strikes. When you hit with your horns, they deal piercing damage equal to 1d6 + your Strength modifier, instead of the bludgeoning damage normal for an unarmed strike.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>Your horns are a natural melee weapon, dealing 1d6 + {{strength:modifier}} piercing damage.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Charge" type="Racial Trait" source="Tome of Heroes" id="ID_KBP_TOH_MINOTAUR_RACIAL_TRAIT_CHARGE">
		<description>
			<p>Once per turn, if you move at least 10 feet toward a target and hit it with a horn attack in the same turn, you deal an extra 1d6 piercing damage and you can shove the target up to 5 feet as a bonus action. At 11th level, when you shove a creature with Charge, you can push it up to 10 feet instead. You can use this trait a number of times per day equal to your Constitution modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet usage="{{charge:uses}}/Long Rest">
			<description>Once per turn, if you move 10 feet or more toward the target and hit it with a horn attack, deal +1d6 piercing damage, and shove the target up to 5 feet as a Bonus Action.</description>
			<description level="11">Once per turn, if you move 10 feet or more toward the target and hit it with a horn attack, deal +1d6 piercing damage, and shove the target up to 10 feet as a Bonus Action.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="charge:uses" value="constitution:modifier" bonus="1" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Labyrinth Sense" type="Racial Trait" source="Tome of Heroes" id="ID_KBP_TOH_MINOTAUR_RACIAL_TRAIT_LABYRINTH_SENSE">
		<description>
			<p>You can retrace without error any path you have previously taken, with no ability check.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You can retrace without error any path you have previously taken, with no ability check.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Bhain Kwai" type="Race Variant" source="Tome of Heroes" id="ID_RACE_VARIANT_MINOTAUR_VARIANT_BHAIN_KWAI">
		<supports>Minotaur</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Bhain kwai are tall and barrel-chested like most minotaurs and have a thin, coarse coat of hair over their bodies. This hair ranges from black and brown to bronze and copper, with occasional rare bhain kwai born with white coats. Bhain kwai hooves are splayed and specially jointed, allowing for easier movement through the muddy terrain they call home. Their horns are upright and curved.</p>
			<p class="indent">These minotaurs make their homes in wet lowlands, often settling in river deltas, marshlands, and rainforests. Bhain kwai prefer small villages to sprawling cities, and they are much less warlike than their cousins. They are still strong and capable, however, and quickly roused to angry retribution if their homeland and people are threatened. Otherwise, the bhain kwai typically apply their mighty statures to caring for the land and to hard labor, able to carry and haul impressive loads for long hours.</p>
			<h4>BHAIN KWAI NAMES</h4>
			<p>Bhain kwai forego family names and descriptors, believing it is the responsibility of all to care for each other and the natural world. When necessary, they identify their villages by the surrounding waters or nearest river or lake, such as “North Shores of Mountain Lake” or “Forest River Delta.”</p>
			<p><span class="feature">Male Names:</span>Dham, Goong, Khemek, Khith, Khoom, Ngai</p>
			<p><span class="feature">Female Names:</span>Dae, Fah, Keo, Nahm, Sano, Xay</p>
			<h4>BHAIN KWAI TRAITS</h4>
			<p>You are a minotaur adapted to life in the bogs and wetlands of the world.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability Score Increase.</em></strong> Your Constitution score increases by 2, and your Strength score increases by 1.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Strong Back.</em></strong> Your carrying capacity is your Strength score multiplied by 20, instead of by 15.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Wetland Dweller.</em></strong> You are adapted to your home terrain. Difficult terrain composed of mud or from wading through water up to waist deep doesn’t cost you extra movement. You have a swimming speed of 25 feet.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false"/>
		<setters>
			<set name="names" type="male">Dham, Goong, Khemek, Khith, Khoom, Ngai</set>
			<set name="names" type="female">Dae, Fah, Keo, Nahm, Sano, Xay</set>
			<set name="names-format">{{name}}</set>
		</setters>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Grants" id="ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_ABILITY_SCORE" />
			<stat name="constitution" value="2" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<stat name="strength" value="1" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
            <select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +2 (Bhain Kwai Minotaur)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 2" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +1 (Bhain Kwai Minotaur)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 1" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<grant type="Grants" id="ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_RACE_MINOTAUR_CHARGE" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_KBP_TOH_MINOTAUR_RACIAL_TRAIT_BHAIN_KWAI_STRONG_BACK" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_KBP_TOH_MINOTAUR_RACIAL_TRAIT_BHAIN_KWAI_WETLAND_DWELLER" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Strong Back" type="Racial Trait" source="Tome of Heroes" id="ID_KBP_TOH_MINOTAUR_RACIAL_TRAIT_BHAIN_KWAI_STRONG_BACK">
		<description>
			<p>Your carrying capacity is your Strength score multiplied by 20, instead of by 15.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>Your carrying capacity is {{load}}.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="load" value="strength:score" />
			<stat name="load" value="strength:score" />
			<stat name="load" value="strength:score" />
			<stat name="load" value="strength:score" />
			<stat name="load" value="strength:score" />
			<stat name="load" value="strength:score" />
			<stat name="load" value="strength:score" />
			<stat name="load" value="strength:score" />
			<stat name="load" value="strength:score" />
			<stat name="load" value="strength:score" />
			<stat name="load" value="strength:score" />
			<stat name="load" value="strength:score" />
			<stat name="load" value="strength:score" />
			<stat name="load" value="strength:score" />
			<stat name="load" value="strength:score" />
			<stat name="load" value="strength:score" />
			<stat name="load" value="strength:score" />
			<stat name="load" value="strength:score" />
			<stat name="load" value="strength:score" />
			<stat name="load" value="strength:score" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Wetland Dweller" type="Racial Trait" source="Tome of Heroes" id="ID_KBP_TOH_MINOTAUR_RACIAL_TRAIT_BHAIN_KWAI_WETLAND_DWELLER">
		<description>
			<p>You are adapted to your home terrain. Difficult terrain composed of mud or from wading through water up to waist deep doesn’t cost you extra movement. You have a swimming speed of 25 feet.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>Difficult terrain composed of mud or waist-high water doesn't cost extra movement.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="speed:swim" value="25" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Boghaid" type="Race Variant" source="Tome of Heroes" id="ID_RACE_VARIANT_MINOTAUR_VARIANT_BOGHAID">
		<supports>Minotaur</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Unlike their cousins, these minotaurs prefer the highlands, living in hilly areas and mountain valleys. Most boghaid live in temperate climes, but some clans have moved even further north into subarctic areas. Boghaid are rugged and sturdy folk, adapted to the colder climes in which they live. They are covered in thick curly hair, growing longer and thicker on the top of the head, shoulders, back, and chest. Hair color ranges from black and dark brown to russet and fawn. Their large horns sweep out to the sides from the head before curling forward.</p>
			<p class="indent">Boghaid have a written language, but most of what is written is carved in stone. Their history and culture are primarily preserved in story and song, passed from one generation to the next during festivals and gatherings. Elders sing and tell tales to the younger boghaid, who learn the tales over time before passing them on to the next generation.</p>
			<h4>BOGHAID NAMES</h4>
			<p>Instead of descriptors, boghaid minotaurs have clan names. These names derive from the mighty heroes of their people that led them to the highlands and founded the first clans. These names are proceeded by the appropriate patronymic: ac, meaning “son of ”; ae, meaning “daughter of ”; or am, meaning “offspring of ”. Hence, the full name of the female boghaid Eva from Clan Torcall would be Eva Ae Torcall.</p>
			<p><span class="feature">Male Names:</span>Aodhan, Baltair, Cormag, Ellair, Munga, Solamh, Ualraig</p>
			<p><span class="feature">Female Names:</span>Aimil, Beitris, Curstag, Eva, Morag, Silis, Una</p>
			<p><span class="feature">Clan Names:</span>Anabla, Barabal, Ceit, Elasaid, Gill‑Ethain, Manus, Raghnall, Torcall</p>
			<h4>BOGHAID TRAITS</h4>
			<p>You are a minotaur adapted to life in cold climates and high altitudes.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability Score Increase.</em></strong> Your Wisdom score increases by 2, and your Constitution score increases by 1.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Highlander.</em></strong> You are adapted to life at high altitudes, and you suffer no ill effects or penalties from elevations above 8,000 feet.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Storied Culture.</em></strong> You have proficiency in the Performance skill, and you gain proficiency with one of the following musical instruments: bagpipes, drum, horn, or shawm.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Wooly.</em></strong> Your thick, wooly coat of hair keeps you warm, allowing you to function in cold weather without special clothing or gear. You have advantage on saving throws against spells and other effects that deal cold damage.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false"/>
		<setters>
			<set name="names" type="male">Aodhan ac, Baltair ac, Cormag ac, Ellair ac, Munga ac, Solamh ac, Ualraig ac</set>
			<set name="names" type="female">Aimil ae, Beitris ae, Curstag ae, Eva ae, Morag ae, Silis ae, Una ae</set>
			<set name="names" type="clan">Anabla, Barabal, Ceit, Elasaid, Gill‑Ethain, Manus, Raghnall, Torcall</set>
			<set name="names-format">{{name}} {{clan}}</set>
		</setters>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Grants" id="ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_ABILITY_SCORE" />
			<stat name="wisdom" value="2" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<stat name="constitution" value="1" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
            <select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +2 (Bhain Kwai Minotaur)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 2" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Custom Ability Score Improvement +1 (Bhain Kwai Minotaur)" supports="Custom Ability Score Increase 1" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
			<grant type="Grants" id="ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_RACE_MINOTAUR_CHARGE" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_KBP_TOH_MINOTAUR_RACIAL_TRAIT_BOGHAID_HIGHLANDER" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_KBP_TOH_MINOTAUR_RACIAL_TRAIT_BOGHAID_STORIED_CULTURE" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_KBP_TOH_MINOTAUR_RACIAL_TRAIT_BOGHAID_WOOLY" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Highlander" type="Racial Trait" source="Tome of Heroes" id="ID_KBP_TOH_MINOTAUR_RACIAL_TRAIT_BOGHAID_HIGHLANDER">
		<description>
			<p>You are adapted to life at high altitudes, and you suffer no ill effects or penalties from elevations above 8,000 feet.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You suffer no ill effects or penalties from elevations above 8,000 feet.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Storied Culture" type="Racial Trait" source="Tome of Heroes" id="ID_KBP_TOH_MINOTAUR_RACIAL_TRAIT_BOGHAID_STORIED_CULTURE">
		<description>
			<p>You have proficiency in the Performance skill, and you gain proficiency with one of the following musical instruments: bagpipes, drum, horn, or shawm.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<select type="Proficiency" name="Instrument Proficiency (Storied Culture)" supports="ID_PROFICIENCY_TOOL_PROFICIENCY_BAGPIPES|ID_PROFICIENCY_TOOL_PROFICIENCY_DRUM|ID_PROFICIENCY_TOOL_PROFICIENCY_HORN|ID_PROFICIENCY_TOOL_PROFICIENCY_SHAWM" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Wooly" type="Racial Trait" source="Tome of Heroes" id="ID_KBP_TOH_MINOTAUR_RACIAL_TRAIT_BOGHAID_WOOLY">
		<description>
			<p>Your thick, wooly coat of hair keeps you warm, allowing you to function in cold weather without special clothing or gear. You have advantage on saving throws against spells and other effects that deal cold damage.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You do not need cold weather gear and you have advantage on saving throws against spells and other effects that deal cold damage.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<!-- Feature Replacement Grants -->
	<element name="Ability Score Feature Replacement" type="Grants" source="Internal" id="ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_ABILITY_SCORE" />
	<element name="Darkvision Feature Replacement" type="Grants" source="Internal" id="ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_VISION_DARKVISION" />
	<element name="Natural Attacks Feature Replacement" type="Grants" source="Internal" id="ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_RACE_MINOTAUR_NATURAL_ATTACKS" />
	<element name="Charge Feature Replacement" type="Grants" source="Internal" id="ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_RACE_MINOTAUR_CHARGE" />
	<element name="Labyrinth Sense Feature Replacement" type="Grants" source="Internal" id="ID_INTERNAL_FEATURE_REPLACEMENT_RACE_MINOTAUR_LABYRINTH_SENSE" />
</elements>
